# Yu-Shiang Huang

Fo9946004@ntu.edu.tw https://www.linkedin.com/in/yu-shiang-huang-309108126/

June 9, 2024

#### **Summary**

I am a Ph.D. candidate in Data Science at National Taiwan University. My research interests include retrieval-enhanced machine learning, natural language processing, and recommender systems, with a particular focus on their applications in the financial domain.

## Education

PhD	<b>National Taiwan University</b> Data Science	Since 2022
MS	<b>National Taiwan University</b> Data Science	Admitted to the Ph.D. program in September 2022.
BS	National Taiwan University	2020

### **Positions**

# Academia Sinica

Accounting

Graduate Student Researcher September 2020-present

Taipei, Taiwan

- NLP in Finance Research: Designed task formulation and an end-to-end retrieval-augmented pipeline to extract important signals from financial reports.
- Recommendation Research: Designed experiments to validate the effectiveness of a new loss function compared to state-of-the-art (SOTA) recommendation methods.
- Recommendation Industry Cooperation: Researched multi-behavior algorithms for banner recommendation systems and deployed the developed model in a real-world system with millions of users.
- NLP Research: Analyzed the characteristics of financial annual reports and designed a new algorithm to classify sentence relations based on these findings. Leveraging the results, we conducted transfer learning in a self-supervised setting, and our paper was accepted by ACL 2023.
- NLP Industry Cooperation: Fine-tuned BERT with a Siamese network and contrastive loss to obtain sentence embeddings in legal data, building a retrieval system aimed at finding the most relevant internal regulations.

National Taiwan University
Taipei, Taiwan

Head Teaching Assistant, CSIE5043 Machine Learning
September 2023-January 2024

- Teaching Assistance: Led a team of 10 to assist in lecturing Machine Learning at National Taiwan University.
- Project Design: Designed the final project and maintained the data streaming pipeline.
- Homework Validation: Validated the homework problem sets related to machine learning theory.

## National Taiwan University

Taipei, Taiwan

Teaching Assistant, CSIE5043 Machine Learning September 2021-January 2022

- Final Project Design: Created an in-class competition for a 300-student course by adding noise to an open dataset and testing competition metrics with various machine learning models.
- Assignment Validation and Consulting: Validated assignments to ensure accuracy in problem sets and provided answers to machine learning theory-related questions during TA hours.

**National Taiwan University** Teaching Assistant, GENEDU5010 Programming and Web Scraping

Taipei, Taiwan

Febuary 2021-June 2021

Instructional Support: Possessed a background in designing programming assignments and offering instructional support, allowing me to contribute effectively to teaching endeavors.

beBit Inc.

Taipei, Taiwan

Part-time Quantitative Analyst October 2020-March 2021

- Survey Data Analysis: Collaborated with a qualitative research team and applied statistical methods to verify business hypotheses and identify key factors in the customer experience journey.
- Methodology Establishment: Improved quantitative analysis methodology based on research papers and technical blogs, enhancing the persuasiveness of the final deliverable.

# **BluePlanet Technology**

Taipei, Taiwan

Project Assistant November 2019-Febuary 2021

- Product Mechanism Design: Surveyed literature related to accounting and regulation to support the product mechanism design, resulting in the successful launch of the product in January 2021.
- Communication: Bridged the gap between the finance research group and the product management team by facilitating communication and recording discussion details during meetings.

## National Taiwan University

Taipei, Taiwan

Part-time Research Assistant July 2020-September 2020

- Website Development at Department of Economics: Utilized Python to create a website for an economics experiment based on a research paper in experimental economics, catering to a participant pool of 100 individuals.

Academia SinicaInternTaipei, TaiwanJuly 2019-June 2020

- Publication: Completed and submitted the work "NFinBERT: A Number-Aware Language Model for Financial Disclosures" to SwissText 2021, which has been accepted.
- Textual Data Analysis: Implemented machine learning models to conduct experiments on the relationship between financial report text and financial measures.
- Experimental Data Preparation: Collected SEC 10-K filings from 1993 to 2018 and performed data cleansing on the corpus through shell scripting, making the 330 GB data available for further research.

## **National Taiwan University**

Taipei, Taiwan

Teaching Material Assistant November 2018-January 2019 - Teaching Material Creation at Department of Electronic Engineering: Self-studied advanced topics about kernel tricks in Support Vector Machines (SVM) in machine learning. Developed teaching slides with explainable examples beyond textbooks, aimed at making the theorems easier to understand.

#### **Publications**

#### **Under Review**

Yu-Shiang Huang, Shih-Yang Liu, Cheng-Wei Lin, and Chuan-Ju Wang. DAGCF: Distance-aware Graph Collaborative Filtering. 2024. Under review

## **Conference Papers**

Jia-Huei Ju, Yu-Shiang Huang, Cheng-Wei Lin, Che Lin, and Chuan-Ju Wang. A compare-and-contrast multistage pipeline for uncovering financial signals in financial reports. In Proceedings of the 61st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 1: Long Papers), pages 14307–14321, 2023

Ta-Wei Huang, Jia-Huei Ju, Yu-Shiang Huang, Cheng-Wei Lin, Yi-Shyuan Chiang, and Chuan-Ju Wang. FISH: A Financial Interactive System for Signal Highlighting. In *Proceedings* of the 17th Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics: System Demonstrations, pages 50–56, 2023

Hao-Lun Lin, Jr-Shian Wu, Yu-Shiang Huang, Ming-Feng Tsai, and Chuan-Ju Wang. NFinBERT: A Number-Aware Language Model for Financial Disclosures (short paper). In *SwissText*, 2021

## Service

## Organizational Leadership

ccClub, a Python Community, Director and Teaching Assitant, 2018-2024

## **Skills**

Extensive programming Python experience on machine learning projects in Linux environment. Extensive experience with machine learning related packages like pytorch, transformers, langchain, sklearn, numpy, pandas and matplotlib. English fluency.

## References

Available on request.